Hello and welcome to the fight against
the rabbit hole.
Okay, let's see. What are we going to
cover today? Today uh we're going to
cover what's the rabbit hole for me,
where do I usually find rabbit holes, h
a prep way uh to fight those rabbit
holes, and an ins way to fight those.
Okay, so let's start. What is the rabbit
hole? For me, the rabbit hole could be
several things, but mostly it it's what
happen when you're falling into a
situation and you don't have the
control. Okay, so where do I usually
find rabbit holes?
Trying to fix something.
Yes, those plus 99 uh tabs open. Uh
trying to understand some code. Yes.
Clicking into endless functions to
functions from class to class. Going
deeper and deeper and deeper and not
being able to understand anything.
Trying to understand an unclear ticket.
Trying to see what they were trying to
say at the moment that they create that
ticket.
Trying to find a solution in a group
meeting. O that's an important one. Yes,
those endless meetings jumping to one
point to the other. H
this is normal of course, but those take
me through the rabbit hole and
I bet that you can find a lot more
examples in your daily work life. Okay,
so a little bit disclaimer. This is
okay. Yes, this is completely normal. is
part of your of the work that we do and
it's part of the learning process of
each person. Okay? So this is an
important disclaimer.
H so don't be afraid if you feel more
than related with all the situations
that I'm saying right now.
So let's talk about some solutions.
Usually I find two ways to fight against
the rabbit holes. Okay? A preventive way
and an easy to way. Okay, let's start by
the preventive way.
So the first thing that we need to do is
to start by doing good questions. Okay.
So do we have the power to see the
future and predict a rabbit hole? No.
Are we geniuses and we didn't know? No.
H do we have super powers and we didn't
know again the answer is no
we are only humans h but we can see this
before it start happening and this is
the way I try to fix it so
first tool ticket refinement this will
become one of your best friends so ask
for clear acceptance criteria the
acceptance criteria
needs needs to be useful to create a
test to understand if the ticket is 100%
complete. Ask for dev resources. What is
this? For example,
where these implementations belongs to
what of the several microser that we are
working. H this belongs to what function
to what class? H do we have similar pers
with things that we did? Erh, this
feature has a flow diagram or doesn't.
This feature have a document or it
doesn't. This feature have a test plan
or it doesn't.
What are the upstream service h impacted
by this? And what are the downstream
service impacted by this?
This maybe seems a pretty obvious
question, but we don't always have the
answer for these ones. Okay? So, it's
important to make these questions on the
ticket refinement to try to understand,
to try to have a better view. And you
may say, hey, I'm working here since
like two or three years ago. So, I have
this thought. Maybe you have that. Maybe
other people's don't maybe other people
start working on the micros service that
you were working and they start chasing
things and now you're going to start
failing into this rabbit hole. So it's
good to have this information there just
as a resource. Okay. Just to be able to
make the things easier for us in the
future. Okay.
Yeah,
I know. But Ramito, I'm a shy person. I
don't like to speak in public.
So, we can always ask uh for the ticket
beforehand and leave the question there.
That's a pretty good practice. You can
say to your PM, to your technical lead,
to whoever is running the refinement.
Hey, can you give me the list of ticket
that we are going to refine in this
session? So, you can read those ticket
and leave questions right there. That
would be good.
But Romero, I don't like to leave a lot
of comments here and there. So, you can
always use the PC of a coworker that
left unblocked when he went to the
bathroom.
Maybe this is not feasible right now due
to the home office. But it's just a
shock. H
But Romeo, if I make all of these
questions, the team is going to hate me.
Yes and no. The team will maybe hate you
at first, but they will love you after
they work on ticket like this. We all
need those kind of things that make us
easy to start getting into the flow and
then be able to uh flow without any
problems instead of instead of getting
stuck in the middle of the flow. Okay,
but Romero, if I ask all these
questions, the refinement will never
finish.
Okay, maybe you will need to reschedule
the refinement at first time. Maybe the
team will be able to refine less tickets
at first time. But with time, I can
assure you that the ticket will start
coming very refined. You will start
needing to make less work.
And of course, this is a long process
from a team to learn and to get these
good practices.
Okay, now let's go to in the [ __ ]
hallway
and clear ticket appear. What should I
do? Destroy the computer.
Shout. No, there is no need to do
anything of that.
The power of making questions.
Use the ticket comments to make a list
of questions that you don't understand.
Try to answer those questions. Write who
can answer those questions. Write the
steps you think will take to solve this.
Write the person that can validate that.
Do a planet 15 meeting with the correct
people.
Send the comments with these questions
before the meeting. Follow the questions
to improve your thinking and take note
and confirm with them before leaving the
meeting.
Post this comment and the answer and
always ask for a thumbs up.
I know this seems a lot but again we are
going to come back to the same concept.
These are good practices that are going
to be built in you and on the team
through the years. This is not going to
be a one day process. This is not going
to be I see this talk and I imple
managed to implement these old things.
Neither will be I see this talk and I
see the benefit of this at the moment.
This is going to be a long-term thing,
but you're going to end up working much
better. And you may say, are you really
doing this? And one day I had to
implement some of these. And these are
the questions that I have when I get
asked to help a team that have a pretty
complex things. And this is how we did
it. I start creating the questions. I
create the meeting. I put the click on
all the things that I was right. And I
the questions and I ask for the thumb
ups. These are a lot of questions. I
don't want you to read this. There is no
need. But this is visible and it's easy
to do once you get used to it.
Questions for other teams. Do you have a
help channels to post clear and concise
questions? That will be the way to go.
Try to do the third the things first in
a channel for those specific teams and
not go to specific persons just to be
able to have h more answers and more
people visualizing that and maybe giving
you ideas that the other people that you
already know doesn't have.
uh
you uh use the ticket to link those
threads there to have the documentation
and an easy way uh to go back to those
that discussion instead of being
searching for all over Slack or Teams or
whatever tool are you using to
understand where was that discussion
that you did. erh bother people. If
there is no answer, leverage your
amazing manager, okay?
They are there to help you and you are
not going to be bothered people if you
always ask the things nice and in a good
way.
So, let's slide the shoe.
Did you write the list of steps to solve
this?
Let's read that again. Sometimes we only
lost focus. Okay, it's pretty normal to
start getting into a thing. Okay, and
getting lost in the middle of the
problem or getting derailed to some
other minor problem, we need to go back
to the main focus. And if you have to
solve something that suddenly appear,
try to create a back ticket and move
forward with your work and then you can
come back to that. Don't try to solve
all the problems at the same time.
That's not a good thing to do.
Use TDD baby steps and test those steps.
This will help you a lot to have little
confirmations that the things that you
are doing are in the right way. This
should be also with the single
responsibility pattern and with a lot of
good practice that will help you write a
small code, easily tested, no not in a
very complex way or needed a lot of
mocking and a lot of those things. So
try to fight one battle at a time. You
did all of this and you are still
falling to the rabbit hole. Left
comments on the code with what you
tried.
Comment the code and say I tried moving
this variable to blah. I tried doing
blah example one, example two, blah blah
blah blah blah. So when you have a
meeting with someone to help you, it
will be easier to explain what did you
did. Sometimes we start trying a lot of
things and suddenly we just forgot or we
have all the things so messed up in your
mind that we don't know what are all the
things that we trying. Okay. So it's
good to leave their crumbers I think it
is the word. H but it's good to leave
the comments there. Here is an example.
Try to filter by using the date column
and don't get what I expected. Try to
filter by combining the date and the
value and I didn't get what I expected.
Uh realize that we were missing some
index and we don't get what we expect
either.
I'm completely lost. Nothing works.
Yeah, the the final comment maybe it's a
lot. But h you see here you will be able
to say hey I tried this. I tried this. I
try this and I also find this other
problem that could be a back ticket that
we solve later. Okay, pair up my friend.
Pair up. This is a great advice. Never
underestimate the power of pairing with
other people.
Explain the problem to someone else. Use
your knowledge. You don't need to know
it all. We, for me at least, our work is
to learn things and to try to do things
that we don't know how to do. So make
the peace with that. You don't need to
know any everything. You will not
believe how many times the solution just
came to your mind once you are trying to
explain the problem to someone else.
Let's have some tea.
Endless meetings. First, be active to
take notes. Ask questions to clarify
what you are not understanding. If
needed, repeat what you understand in
order to make sure that we are talking
about the same things.
This sound pretty silly, but it's a
powerful tool to use to really be sure
that we are talking about the same
things. When you have five minutes, read
the notes, confirm mutual understanding,
and write new questions and offer to
schedule a new meeting. Those endless
meetings drain your mind or at least
mine and end up going like backwards in
the process. So say hey
we complete the time for this meeting
let's reschedule and this will be the
topics for the next meeting.
So do I manage to implement each of
these things every day?
No. But when I do, I work happier h and
I spend more time in the flow that uh
dealing with unnecessary things.
Thank you. If you have any comments,
ideas, suggestions, let me know. I know
this is not the perfect way, but these
are some tips that really help me h and
help the people that I work with. So, if
you have better ideas, let me know. We
can discuss it and I maybe could add it
to this or another video. So, have a
good day and thanks